<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A prognostication made for the yeare of our Lorde God, 1572 wherein at large is set forth the description of the fovver quarters of the yeare, with the prediction of the weather for euery day, exactly calculated for Oxenforde. By Thomas Hill, of London student.]</title>
            <author>Hill, Thomas, b. ca. 1528.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 459.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118792</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853999</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19404</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17928)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19404)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 570:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A prognostication made for the yeare of our Lorde God, 1572 wherein at large is set forth the description of the fovver quarters of the yeare, with the prediction of the weather for euery day, exactly calculated for Oxenforde. By Thomas Hill, of London student.]</title>
                  <author>Hill, Thomas, b. ca. 1528.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8+] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard VVatkins, and Iames Roberts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1572]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint taken from subsidiary title page.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 13501.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; prognostication only, with several leaves missing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meteorology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19404:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19404:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Prognostication made</hi> for the yeare of our Lorde God, 1572. wherein at large is ſet forth the deſcription of the fower quarters of the yeare, with the prediction of the weather for euery day, exactly calculated for Oxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde.</p>
            <p>By Thomas Hill, of London Student.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London</hi> by Richard VVatkins, and Iames Roberts.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19404:2"/>
            <head>¶ The nature and qualitie of the .xij. ſignes, after the principles of Phiſik.</head>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> moyſt than hote.</item>
               <item>Taurus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erate and moyſteſt.</item>
               <item>Gemini, more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> than moyſt.</item>
               <item>Cancer, more hote than drie.</item>
               <item>Leo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt and drieſt.</item>
               <item>Virgo, more drie than hote.</item>
               <item>Libra, more drie than colde.</item>
               <item>Scorpio, coldeſt and drieſt.</item>
               <item>Sagittarius, more colde than drie.</item>
               <item>Capricorne, more cold than moyſt.</item>
               <item>Aquarius, moſt colde and moyſt.</item>
               <item>Piſces, more moyſt than colde.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="description_of_eclipse_of_the_moon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19404:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Of the Eclipſe of the Moone, which ſhall appeare to vs, this yeare of our redemption. 1572.</head>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>THis preſent yere of our Lord God. <hi>1572.</hi> being the .xxv. of June, at .viij. of the clocke, &amp; .lvi. min. in the night ſhall appere and be ſeene aboue our Horizon, a particuler Eclipſe of the Moone, ſhee then beeing at hir full, and right againſt the Sunne: Into the ſhadowe of the earth ſhee ſhall come to be Eclypſed, about .xvi. mi. before .ix. a clocke, and to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly ſeene, both of Canterburie and London, about .x. min. after .ix. and ende this Eclipſe about .x. a clock at Oxford: ſo that in this darkneſſe ſhe ſhall tarrie about one howre, and a quarter, and be ſhadowed of the earth only v. points &amp; .iiij. mi. Southerly, nere to that ſection, named the Dragons taile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in the .xiij. degree, and .xxiiij. minuts of <hi>Capricorne:</hi> Certaine ſpecial effects of this Moones Eclipſe, are vttered in the Harueſt quarter: in that theſe ſhall begin to worke and ſhew their harmes to the earth, about the .xiiij. of October, in the yeare. <hi>1572.</hi> and ende the xxij. of December folowing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="description_of_four_quarters_of_the_year">
            <pb facs="tcp:19404:3"/>
            <head>¶ A Deſcription, of the fower <hi>quarters of the yeare, beginning</hi> the twelth day of December, in the yeare. 1571.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of the Wynter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He later Aſtronomers inſtruct, that the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quarter Aſtronomicall of this preſent yeare of our Lord. <hi>1572.</hi> is already begunne, and beganne with vs the .xij. day of December, at .vi. of the clock at night, in the yeare. <hi>1571.</hi> at which tyme the Sunne entred into the firſt min. of <hi>Capricorne.</hi> This winter quarter &amp; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, reported (of the wiſe and learned) to be of the owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſpoſition and qualitie, colde and moyſt, contrary to the condition of Summer, whoſe enimie he is founde to be, (for that in all reſpectes, it deſtroyeth thoſe creſcent thinges, which Sommer hath brought forth, &amp; nouriſhed by his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heate) will this yeare anſwere, to the naturall kinde. For in the beginning of this quarter, it appeareth to be enclined to bitter colde, &amp; vnconſtant weather, with ſodaine ſhowers and ſoutherly winds, toward the midſt more bent to ſtormy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as haile, bluſtering winds, great ſhowres of raine, ſnow, clowdie, and darke weather, with Landfloudes after rayne, more ryfe in this ſeaſon: whoſe violence, when theſe ſhalbe of force, are like to cauſe Eruptions or braſtinges forth of the Earth in lowe places, and that Springes of water to breake vp, in ſuch abundaunce: that both Men, and Cattell ſhall be greatly annoyed therewith: Further, colde miſtes, and darke fogges, with horie froſtes, and bitter colde weather, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:19404:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>harme to Cattell, as Horſe, Oxen, Kyen, Sheepe, and ſuch like: yea to fowles of the winter, and fiſhes of that ſeaſon: to Fruytes, and Gardine hearbes, and to Corne of all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode: but theſe (thanked bee God) not ſo harmefull, to bee looked for of vs: in that paſt a thyrde part, and ſomewhat more, of the Moonee body entreth then into ſhadow: which the learned alſo report, to threaten leſſe harme to the earth. As touching the ſickneſſes and diſeaſes, that are like to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in this quarter: be thoſe proceeding of colde and to much moyſture, and Melancholy humours, agreeing to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Harueſt, and ſundrie of the Sommer diſeaſes repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and hapning in this ſeaſon. As all the kindes of feuers, with the peſtilent Ague, ſtraightneſſe in the breaſt, pluriſies, weakneſſe of the Liuer, and ſtomacke, opilation or ſtopping of the Splene, grieuous paynes of the head, the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, rewmes, <hi>Opthalmies,</hi> running of the eyes, long laſting ſickneſſes, the quartayne Ague, of Melancholie, blacke Iaundiſe, dropſies, ſwellings and ache in the legges, knees, and feete, ſuffocations and obſtructions of the Matrice, the perilous cough, waterie laxes, the pyles, <hi>Gonorrhea</hi> weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the backe, the Letharge, the Gowte, and ſuch lyke: which the Lorde for a due puniſhment of Sinne, worketh by his inſtruments the ſtarres: Yet God of his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, doth giue to vs meanes many tymes, to be deliuered and holpen, by ſeeking in time to the learned and well practiſed Phyſition: a commended and worthy inſtrument of his on earth, for that purpoſe. To whom in ſuch tymes of perill, I would wiſhe (all perſons of abilitie) to reſorte vnto, for aduiſe and counſayle: God the true and principalleſt Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be our comforter, and deliuer our bodies from the contageon and infections threatned vs by the ſtarres, in this diſtemperate time of Harueſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prognostications_of_weather">
            <pb facs="tcp:19404:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The predictions of the daylye ſtate</hi> and condition of the weather euery day in the weeke, throughout the .xii. moneths of this preſent yeare of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. 1572.</head>
            <div type="month">
               <head>¶ Of Ianuarie.</head>
               <p>THe firſt day clowdie, rawe colde with ſome moyſture and winde in the morning, after fayre. The ſecond, fayre, colde, and windie: the thirde colde and drie, with ſome winde: the fourth clowdie, colde, with ſome ſnow and winde: the fift raw colde, and diſpoſed to winde and raine: the ſixt dark clowdes, wind ſouth, and raine: the .vii. darke, and miſtie ayre, with ſome rayne, and winde.</p>
               <p>☽ Laſt quarter the .viij. day at .xi. of the clock, &amp; three min. before noone, colde, clowdie, ſmall raine or ſnowe, and windie. The .ix. clowdie, rawe colde, and enclyned to ſnow, wind foutherly: the .x. raw colde, enclyned to moyſture: the .xi ſome raine, clowdie, and bigge winde: the .xij. raine in the morning, after drie and colde, at night froſt: the .xiij. clowdie, rawe colde, with raine in the forenoone, after drie and windie: the .xiiii. clowdie, and enclyned to moyſture, about noone and towards night, drie and colde.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> New Moone the .xv. day, at vij. of the clocke, and vi. min. in the morning, raw colde, darke clowdes, windie, with ſome ſnow or raine towardes the euening. The .xvi. colde, &amp; darke weather, with ſmall raine &amp; winde, but at night drie, and a froſt: the .xvii. windie, and colde: the .xviii. clowdy with a little winde and ſmall rayne, after fayre: the .xix. en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyned to ſnowe, or ſharpe weather, and darke clowdes: the xx. ſome ſmall rayne, and winde.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19404:4"/>
☾ Firſt quarter the .xxi. day, at .xij. of the clock, and .xlviij. min. in the night, moyſt, clowdie, and darke weather, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noone, and afterwardes, more temperate, and drie: the xxii. clowdie, colde, and wind about midnight: the .xxiii. cold, clowdie and wind, but at euening a froſt: the .xxiiii. drie, with winde at night: the .xxv. colde, and fayre weather: the .xxvi. clowdie, colde, with ſome raine, about noone fayre, and froſt at night: the .xxvii. ſharpe ayre, clowdie or miſtie, after noone fayre weather: the .xxviii. clowdie, with ſome winde, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to raine, but at after noone, drie weather and a froſt at night: the .xxix. a fayre morning and colde, towards nyght o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercaſt with blacke clowdes.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonround">❍</g> Full Moone the .xxx. day, at two of the clocke, and xxviij. min. in the morning, rawe colde and darke with rayne, and winde: the .xxxi. clowdie and colde weather, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde night a bigge winde or raine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <head>Februarie.</head>
               <p>THe firſt day clowdie, and enclining to ſnowe or rayne, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards night a froſt: the ſeconde colde, windie, and darke in the morning, after fayre, and a froſt at night: the third in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different fayre, with clowdes, and ſome wynde at night: the fourth drie and fayre weather, &amp; a bigge winde in the night: the fift clowdie, colde, with winde: the ſixt windy, blacke clowdes, and ſome rayne or ſnowe.</p>
               <p>☽ Laſt quarter the .vij. day at one of the clocke .xxij. min. in the morning, rawe colde, darke weather, ſome rayne or ſnowe, and windie: the .viii. clowdie, colde, with rayne and winde, towarde night, drie: the .ix. rawe colde, clowdie, and ſmall rayne with winde: the .x. clowdie, darke weather, and ſtormie, and ſodaine colde ſhowers or ſnowe: the .xi. darke, and colde, with ſome rayne towarde noone: the .xii. clowdie, rapping colde, and windie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19404:5"/>
                  <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> New Moone the xiij. day, at .iiij. of the clocke .lviij. mi. in the after noone, colde and raynie, or ſome ſhowers, with winde, Weſterly. The .xiiii. clowdie, temperate, with ſome milde rayne and winde: the .xv. darke and clowdie with ſmall raine, in the after noone fayre with winde: the .xvi. drie &amp; fayre, at night windie, &amp; clowdie: the .xvii. fayre and warme all the day, vnto night: the .xviii. colde, with darke clowdes, &amp; ſome winde or rayne about noone, or at night: the .xix. tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate weather, with clowdes, &amp; ſome winde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> after noone.</p>
               <p>☾ Firſt quarter the .xx. day at .iiij. of the clocke, and .xij. min. in the after noone, fayre and colde, with winde nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly: the .xxi. variable, clowdie. with winde or rayne: the xxii. colde, clowdie, with raine: the .xxiii. fayre, colde, with ſmall winde, and froſt at night: the .xxiiii. ſharper weather with blacke cowdes, and enclyned to rayne or ſnowe: the xxv. fayre and warme, with froſt at night: the .xxvi. ſharper weather, with blacke clowdes. and winde: and enclyned to ſnow or colde raine: the .xxvii. clowdie, colde, and dark, with winde.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonround">❍</g> Full Moone the .xxviij. day, at .viij. of the clocke, and xxxv. mi. in the night, darke ayre, raine &amp; windie, with ſome ſtorme: the .xxix. clowdie, rawe colde, with ſome muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to winde, colde rayne or ſnowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <head>March.</head>
               <p>THe firſt day fayre and warme, with clowdes in the after noone, and ſome winde: the ſecond, great winde or a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, with rayne in the morning: the thirde clowdie, colde, and ſome rayne in the morning: the fourth, darker ayre, raw cold, and enclyning to moyſture: the fift clowdie, colde with ſome rayne towardes the after noone: The .vi. clowdie, colde, with bigge winde or raine towarde midnight, after fayre.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:19404:5"/>
               <p>noone: the .vii. windie, and clowdie in the forenone, after tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and milde ayre: the .viii. fayre and warme al the day, but at night rayne, and winde: the .ix. a fayre and hote day, vnto night.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> Newe Moone the .x. day, at .xx. min. after hygh noone, hote, after clowdie, with big wind, &amp; ſodaine ſhowers. The .xi. clowdie, with ſome rayne, and bigge winde: the .xii. clowdie and enclined to rayne, with ſome ſmall winde in the after noone: the .xiii. fayre and hote, all the day: the .xiiii. like fayre and hote, vnto night: the .xv. a fayre and very hote day, without winde in effect: the .xvi. clowdie, and temperate in the forenoone, after hote vnto night: the .xvii. a hote and fayre day, with ſome winde about noone.</p>
               <p>☾ Firſt quarter the .xviij. day, at two of the clock, and .xx. min. in the after noone, enclyned to thunder, bigge wind and ſhowers, with thicke clowdes, and ſulthie hote or, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable ayre. The .xix. windie, and temperate in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone: the .xx. temperate, with ſome winde, and blacke clowdes about noone: the .xxi. clowdie, and ſulthie hote, and eyther thunder, or hayle: the .xxii. temperate, and enclyned to fayre weather, in the after noone: the .xxiii. fayre and hote, all the day: the .xxiiii. fayre and temperate, in the after noone.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonround">❍</g> Full Moone eclipſed on the .xxv. day, at .viij. of the clock and .lvi. mi. in the night, ſulthie hote, and clowdie, with ſome ſmall winde. The .xxvi. clowdie, temperate, and enclyning to rayne at night: the .xxvii. fayre and warme, with blacke clowdes gathering towards rayne, in the after noone: the .xxviii. fayre and hote all the day, but at night rayne with ſome winde: the .xxix. clowdie, and temperate, with ſome rayne, and winde towardes night: the .xxx. fayre, and hote with ſome winde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:19404:6"/>
               <head>Iulie.</head>
               <p>THe firſt day, a tempeſt, or thunder and lightning, wyth ſome winde in the night.</p>
               <p>☽ Laſt quarter the ſecond day at .xi. of the clocke, and .xv. minuts before noone, heate, after clowdye, with vnſtable weather, and a bigge wind or tempeſt, with wind to the ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt. The thirde temperate, and drie, put in the after noone clowdie, with ſome winde and rayne: the fourth clowdie and darke, with rayne and winde: the fift variable, with rayne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout midnight: the ſixt vnconſtaunt weather, with blacke clowdes enclyning to rayne, in the after noone: the .vii. tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, with winde and blacke clowdes, enclyning to rayne: the .viii. clowdie, temperate, with bigge winde in the after noone: the .ix. temperate &amp; drie, with wind in the after noone.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> Newe Moone the .x. day, at two of the clock, and foure minutes in the morning, clowdie, hote, with ſome ſmal rayne, and windie to the northeſt in the after noone. The xi. fayre and hote, with a tempeſt, or bigge winde in the after noone: the .xii. a fayre and hote day, with ſome winde in the forenoone: the .xiii. clowdie, temperate and drie, with winde toward night: the .xiiii. clowdie towardes rayne in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, after a fayre and hote day: the .xv. ſome winde and clowdes, in the forenoone, after fayre and hote vnto night: the .xvi. white clowdes, with ſome winde, and fayre all the day: the .xvii. a hote and fayre day, with winde in the after noone.</p>
               <p>☾ Firſt quarter the .xviij. day at .v. of the clock, and .xxx. mi. in the morning, fayre &amp; hote weather, towards noone clowdie, and enclyned to rayne, with thunder, and lightning in the after noone. The .xix. temperate and clowdie, towardes rayne, in the forenoone: the .xx. fayre, and hote, with ſome winde: the .xxi. fayre, and hote, with clowdes towarde rayne
<pb facs="tcp:19404:6"/>in the night: the .xxii. clowdie and temperate in the fore noone with ſome winde, but in the after noone blacke clowdes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to a tempeſt or thunder: the .xxiii. clowdie and darke, with bigge winde about noone, and vnto night continuyng: the .xxiii clowdie, and inclined to rayne in the fore noone.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonround">❍</g> Full Moone the .xxv. day, at foure of the clocke, and xivij. min. in the morning, vntemperate heate, wyth darke clowdes towarde rayne, and winde from the ſoutheaſt. The .xxvi. clowdie, towards rayne in the morning, after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different fayre and temperate: the .xxvii. clowdie in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and temperate all the daye: the .xxviii. variable, wyth clowdes gathered towardes rayne in the forenoone, but in the night bigge winde: the .xxix. great winde, with clowdes gathered towardes rayne in the forenoone, after fayre and hote vnto night: the .xxx. fayre and hote in the forenoone, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noone, many white clowdes gathered, and bigge wynde in the after noone.</p>
               <p>☽ Laſt quarter the .xxxi. day, at ſeuen of the clocke and .xi. minuts in the after noone, clowdie, temperate, with ſome rayne in the night, and winde to the ſouthweſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <head>Auguſt.</head>
               <p>THe firſt day fayre, and hote vnto night, about midnight clowdie, with ſome winde: the ſecond variable weather, drie and windie: the thirde windie, ſayre, and warme wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the day: the fourth clowdie, and enclyned to rayne in the forenoone, with winde in the after noone: the fift tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and drie, with white clowdes towardes moyſture, ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ayre: the .vi. temperate, with white clowdes, and winde in the after noone: the .vii. darke clowdes, and encly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to rayne in the forenoone: but after midnight hayle, or thunder and great ſhowers of rayne.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19404:7"/>
                  <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> Newe Moone the viij. day at .v. of the clocke, and .xxiij. minutes in the after noone, darke ayre, and eyther hayle, or thunder and lightning, with a bigge wind from the ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt: the, ix. clowdie in the morning, with ſome rayne, and bigge wynde: in the after noone temperate vnto night: the x. clowdie, towardes rayne and ſome wind: the .xi. fayre and hote all the day, without winde: the .xii. hote and fayre, with clowdes gathered in the after noone, but a fayre night: the xiii. fayre and hote, about noone clowdes, with ſome winde at night: the .xiiii. clowdie, with ſome winde in the forenoone, and hote vnto night: the .xv. darke or blacke clowdes, and bigge winde in the forenoone.</p>
               <p>☾ Firſt quarter the .xvi. day, at .vi. of the clock, and .xliiij. minurs in the after noone, clowdie, and enclined to raine, winte and ſtormie weather. The .xvii. clowdie in the after noone, and fulthie hote all the day: the .xviii. fayre and hote, with white clowdes, and ſome winde in the after noone: the xix. clowdie, and darke about noone: and enclyned to rayne, in the after noone: the .xx. clowdie, and diſpoſed to rayne in the forenoone, with white clowdes, and rayne or winde in the after noone: the .xxi. temperate, and clowdie in the after noone, with winde and rayne: the .xxii. windie, with clowdes and raine or winde at night.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonround">❍</g> Full Moone the .xxiij. day, at .xvi. mi. after high noone, fayre, after enclyned to moyſture, with blacke clowdes, and bigge winde. The .xxiiii. clowdie, and temperate about midnight, more bent to hayle or ſhowers: the .xxv. fayre, and hote all the day: the .xxvi. hote, and fayre with white clowdes gathered in the forenoone: the .xxvij. temperate, and clowdie in the after noone: after midnight a bigge winde or ſtorme, with ſome rayne: the .xxviij. temperate and drie with bigge winde, and clowdes in the after noone: the .xxix. fayre with</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:19404:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>boyſterous wynde, about that tyme: the .xvi. windie, colde, and a ſtorme, or rayne in the morning, after fayre and a froſt at night: the .xvii. colde with winde, and drie vnto night: the xviii. clowdie, and enclyning to rayne in the forenoone: and in the after noone blacke clowdes, and bitter colde winde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to night.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonround">❍</g> Full Moone the .xix, day, at vi. of the clock, and .liii. mi. in the after noone, colde and vnconſtant weather, wyth ſome wind. The .xx. windie, variable, and drie, with clowds towardes rayne, after midnight: the .xxi. colde, and drie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noone enclining to rayne: the .xxii. froſt in the morning, and fayre vnto night: the .xxiii. nipping colde, with winde in the morning, in the after noone bigge winde, and ſome raine: the .xxiiii. froſt, and a fayre warme day vnto night: the .xxv. froſt, and fayre in the morning: but at noone ouercaſt, wyth white and blacke clowdes, and nipping colde towards night: the .xxvi. clowdie, colde, and enclyning to rayne in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, after fayre and drye vnto night.</p>
               <p>☽ Laſt quarter the .xxvii. day, at two of the clock, and foure min. in the after noone, colde and clowdie, with ſome colde miſſing rayne or ſnowe, and winde: the .xxviii. rawe colde, with blacke clowdes to moyſture in the forenoone, &amp; at night winde. The .xxix. fayre, with ſome winde in the morning, and drie vnto night: the .xxx. colde with white clowdes, and winde in the forenoone, and fayre, vnto night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <head>December.</head>
               <p>THe firſt day colde, clowdie, with winde in the morning, and rayne in the after noone: the ſecond fayre, and a hory froſt in the morning, with ſharpe ayre, and drye vnto night, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout midnight ſnowe or colde rayne: the thirde colde, and dry wyth ſome myſt or darkneſſe in the morning, and winde in the night: the fourth fayre, and warme all the daye, with ſome
<pb facs="tcp:19404:8"/>ſmall winde in the after noone.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> Newe Moone, the fift day, at ix. of the clocke, and .xvii. minutes in the morning, clowdie, colde, and a froſt, or colde ſleete. The .vi. rawe colde, and blacke clowdes, with ſome rayne in the after noone: the .vii. colde, with white clowdes and winde in the forenoone, but in the after noone, rawe colde, and darke or miſtie weather vnto night: the .viii. a horie froſt in the morning, wyth wynde in the after noone, and in the night raine, with a bigge wind towards midnight: the .ix. colde, and whyte clowdes wyth wynde in the morning, and a ſmall wynde in the after noone, wyth darke nippyng weather, or a raw cold myſt at night: the .x. fayre and warme, with ſome wynd in the morning: the .xi. temperate and fayre, wyth froſt, or a darke myſt, and wynde in the night.</p>
               <p>☾ Firſt quarter the .xii. day at .v. of the clocke, and .lv. mi. in the morning, rawe colde, and clowdie with froſt or darke myſtes. The .xiii. froſt, and fayre, wyth whyte clowdes, and wynde in the after noone: the .xiiii. colde, myth a ſmall winde in the morning, and fayre vnto night: the .xv. clowdye, colde, and bigge wynde in the morning, with rayne in the after noone: the .xvi. a horyefroſt, or ſharpe myſt in the morning, and winde towardes midnight: the .xvii. colde, and varyable weather, wyth wynde in the after noone: the xviii. a froſt, with whyte clowdes, and wynde in the morning, and fayre vnto nyght.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:Moonround">❍</g> Full Moone the .xix. day at .ix. of the clocke, and. xxxii. minutes in the forenoone, colde and cloſe weather, wyth ſnowe or colde ſleete: the .xx. fayre, and colde, wyth whyte clowdes and wynde, in the forenoone, and myſtie or rawe darke we other at nyght: the .xxi. a ſharpe colde morning, and fayre warme weather vnto nyght, but after mydnight, ſnowe or hayle, or other colde ſhowers of rayne: the .xxii. a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing
<pb facs="tcp:19404:8"/>froſt in the morning, and hote (for the tyme) all the day, with a bigge colde wynde, in the nyght: the .xxiii. bytter colde, or a horye froſt in the morning, with clowdes enclyning to rayne or ſnowe in the forenoone, and ſharpe weather vnto night: the .xxiiii. colde in the morning, with fayre weather all the day, and a horie froſt, at night: the .xxv. froſt, or a colde myſt, and ſmall winde in the morning, with fayre weather vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nyght: the .xxvi. clowdie, cold, with ſome winde, and encly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to moyſture in the forenoone.</p>
               <p>☽ Laſt quarter, the .xxvii. day, at ten of the clock. and .liiii. minutes in the forenoone, moyſt, rawe colde, and clowdie weather, wyth wynde at night. The .xxviii. winde, wyth clowdes cauſing a colde ayre in the mornyng, and indifferent fayre all the day, but at nyght, diſpoſed to ſnowe, or a darke myſt very colde, wyth ſome wynde: the .xxix, a horye froſt, or darke colde myſt in the morning, wyth blacke clowdes or dark, vnto night: the .xxx. clowdie, colde, &amp; darke, or a myſt in the mornyng, with blacke clowdes towardes ſnow, and bigge wynde in the after noone, but in the nyght a ſtorme of hayle, or ſnow wyth bluſtering wynde: the .xxxi. colde, and clowdes towardes ſnowe in the forenoone, and ſharpe or colde myſtye weather vnto nyght.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <trailer>Laudes Deo.</trailer>
               <trailer>Qui fecit luminaria magna, ſolem in poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem diei, lunam in poteſtatem noctis.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="description_of_planets">
            <pb facs="tcp:19404:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the nature and qualitie of the</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Planets, their magnitude, with the ſickneſſes and partes, that they ſeuerally gouerne in man.</head>
            <div type="planet">
               <head>Of Saturne.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAturne,</hi> higheſt of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, being ninetie times with an eyght part greater than the earth, pale (to a leady colour) of moſt ſtowe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, in that hee performmeth not the whole courſe before .xxx. yeres: and reported (to bee an infortime) doth of his nature procure earthquakes, ſnow and hayle, the peſtilence and dearth of victuals. As touching the higheſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention or poynte of <hi>Saturnes</hi> Orbe, from the earth, the ſame is at this day knowne to be in the .xxix. dogree of <hi>Sagittarius.</hi> This <hi>Saturne</hi> by iudgenent of the ſkilfull, hath of Elements, the earth, in that he worketh his proper influence on the ſame. Of complexions or qualities in perſons, this gouerneth melancholike. Of humors in man, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie. Of the proper condicions, heauineſſe, couetouſneſſe, penſiue thoughts, ſuſpition, long ſilence, deception, fearefulneſſe. &amp;c. Of ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, this hath the Quartayne feuer, the blacke iaundyſe, the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Catharre or rewme, the Palſie, the Leproſie, the blacke Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, the Dropſie, the Iliacke paſſion, the flure of the belly of colde humors, the colde Gowte, and ache of the ioyntes, the Canker, harde ſwellings, and kimels (riſing in ſundry parts of the body) and all ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in a maner, being of a colde and due qualitie. To conclude if man, this gouerneth the milt, the right eare, the teeth and bones. Lorde alſo of the firſt howre on Saterday.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19404:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
